07 - Future Tasks of the Alliance - “Harmel Report”
NATO Archives Online
- Purposes and procedure of the Study: composition of the four sub-groups (February 1967 – May 1967), 1967-02 - 1967-05; Volume 2; 62 Items
  - Composition of the Sub-groups on the Future Tasks of the Alliance, Section 5
    - AC/261-N/4. Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. Note on the composition of the four sub-groups. (12 April 1967) BIL 1
    - 2347. Netherlands Delegation. Letter to the Secretary General stating that Dr. Patijn will be the Netherlands Representative for the Sub-group 4 on Developments in regions outside the NATO area. (13 April 1967) ENG 1
    - AC/261-N/5. Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. Note from the Secretary informing the representatives of a change to upcoming meeting times. (14 April 1967) BIL 1
    - AC/261-N/6. Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. Note by the Secretary of the Special Group on the composition of the four sub-groups (14 April 1967) BIL 1
    - List of members attending Sub-group 4 of the Special Group on Future Tasks of the Alliance. (April 1967) FRE 1
    - AC/261-N/4 (Revised). Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. Note on the composition of the four sub-groups. (17 April 1967) BIL 1
    - Canadian Delegation. Letter from Permanent Representative to the Secretary General detailing changes to their representation in the four sub-groups. (8 May 1967) ENG 1
    - AC/261-N/4 (Revised) Addendum. Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. Note on the Canadian changes to the composition of the four sub-groups. (12 May 1967) ENG 1
    - AC/261-N/9. Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. Note detailing changes in the Secretaries of sub-groups 1 and 2. (16 May 1967) BIL 1
    - FCM/67/105. Memo from Fritz. C. Menne appointing Mr. de Burlet acting Secretary of the Special Group for the Future Tasks of the Alliance during the month of July 1967. (27 June 1967) ENG 1
  - Press Release announcing the establishment of the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance and its Sub-groups, Section 6
    - POLADS(67)16. Memorandum from the Committee of Political Advisors. Suggestion for changing the name of sub-group 4 to “Relations with other countries” in draft press release. (12 April 1967) ENG 1
    - DPA/67/95. Political Affairs Division, brief for the Chairman on the Council Meeting on 12 April 1967. (12 April 1967) ENG 1
    - C-R(67)17. NATO Council meeting on 12 April 1967. Extract on a possible press release. (26 April 1967) BIL 1
    - Press Release (67) 3. NATO Press release outlining the subjects studied by the four sub-groups of the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance, and their members. (13 April 1967) BIL 1
  - Remarks by the Secretary General on the occasion of the first series of meetings of the Sub-groups, Section 7
    - Draft for the Chairman’s speech in the meeting of the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance on 17 April 1967, reviewing the work done so far and assessing the work to be done before the ministerial meeting of June 1967. (12 April 1967) ENG 1
    - Opening remarks by the Secretary General at Press Conference. (17 April 1967) ENG 1
    - GAS/67/40. Political Affairs Division, General Affairs Section. Brief for the Chairman on the meeting of the Special Group on 17 April 1967, reviewing the work done so far and assessing the work to be done before the ministerial meeting of June 1967. (14
    - APH/67/102. Memorandum from A. P. Hockaday, raising the question as to whether “external” help should be sought to implement the resolution on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (19 April 1967) ENG 1
    - Summary of a meeting between the Secretary General and rapporteurs of the sub-groups. (18 April 1967) ENG 1
  - The next round of discussions by the four sub-groups to allow the preparation of the interim progress report for the next Ministerial meeting, Section 8
    - FCM/67/64. Memorandum from F.C. Menne outlining the work program for the upcoming round of discussion by the 4 sub-groups of the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (19 April1967) ENG 1
    - FCM/67/76. Memorandum from F.C. Menne suggesting a change of date for the meeting of the 5 rapporteurs and of Sub-group 3. (5 May 1967) ENG 1
    - FCM/67/77. Memorandum confirming the change of date for the meeting of the 5 rapporteurs. (8 May 1967) ENG 1
  - Summary of work done by the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance, Section 9
    - DPA/67/123. Political Affairs Division. Memorandum to Secretary General explaining the Future Tasks of the Alliance, the work performed by the group and the work performed by the sub-groups. (9 May 1967) ENG 1
- National contributions to previous discussion (April 1967 – August 1967), 1967-04 - 1967-08; Volume 3; 21 Items
  - Distribution of necessary documents from previous discussion relating to the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance, Section 1
    - C-VR(59)44. Council Verbatim Record. Speech by Mr. Herter during the Council meeting taking place 15 December 1959 calling for further examination into the “Long range prospects that lie ahead for NATO”. (reissued 28 April 1967) ENG 1
    - C-M(61)30 Part I. Council Memorandum on the development of political consultation. First issued 20 April 1961. ( reissued 28 April 1967) BIL 1
    - C-M(61)30 Part II. Council Memorandum on the development of political consultation. First issued 18 April 1961. (reissued 28 April 1967) BIL 1
    - C-M(61)30 Part III. Council Memorandum on the development of political consultation. First issued 18 April 1961. (reissued 28 April 1967) BIL 1
    - SG(67)160. Secretary General. Request to Mr. Dobson for the reprinting and circulation to Sub-group 2 of documents C-M(61)30, NHO(63)1 and C-VR(59)44 (27 April 1967) FRE 1
    - AC/261-N/7. Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. Note from the Secretary distributing additional documentation for Sub-group 2. (28 April 1967) BIL 1
  - Bibliographic assistance to Sub-group 1, Section 2
    - Common declaration by the United States, UK and France to support the constitution of a free Federal Republic of Germany after its declaration of 3 October 1954. FRE 1
    - RS/67/63. Research Section. International Staff bibliographic assistance to Sub-group 1 “Future of the Alliance” study. (24 April 1967) ENG 1
  - The call for outside experience for the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance, Section 3
    - DPA/67/111. Political Affairs Division. Draft of a letter from the Secretary General asking delegations to bring to the special group’s attention any speeches, parliamentary reports or articles from qualified authors on the future tasks of the Alliance. (
    - AC/261-D/1. Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. Document from Secretary General asking delegations to bring to the special groups’ attention any speeches, parliamentary reports or articles from qualified authors on the future tasks of the A
  - Digest of published material for the Future Tasks of the Alliance, Section 4
    - Selected digest for the use of the special group compiled from books and articles by statemen and recognized writers on international affairs. (May 1967) ENG 1
    - DPA/67/130. Political Affairs Division. Cover note to the digest for the use of the Special Group. (12 May 1967) ENG 1
    - Letter to the ASG Political Affairs from the authors of the digest on changes of form and content of the digest. Followed by handwritten response. (29 May 1967) ENG 1
  - Circulation of APAG’s report on the problem of balance within the Atlantic Alliance in the 1970’s, Section 5
    - DPA/67/118, 121 and 122. Political Affairs Division, Letter to Mr. Spaak from J. Jaenicke on the problem of balance within the Atlantic Alliance in the 1970’s brought out during APAG meeting. (8 May 1967) ENG 1
    - Belgian Delegation. Letter to the Assistant Secretary General for Political Affairs acknowledging Mr. Jaenicke’ letter and assuring that it be passed on to Mr. Spaak. (11 May 1967) FRE 1
    - C-R(67)31. Council meeting on 4 July 1967. Extract on the report by APAG to be submitted to the Special Group on the Future Tasks of Alliance. (20 July 1967) ENG 1
    - RDC/67/240. Note from R.D. Coleridge to Secretaries of delegations, on C-M(67)38 Future Tasks of the Alliance: APAG report on the problem of balance within the Atlantic Alliance in the 1970’s. (18 July 1967) BIL 1
  - Canadian input on the Future Tasks of NATO, Section 6
    - Canadian Delegation. Letter to the Secretary General containing a statement from the Canadian Secretary of State for External Affairs Mr. Paul Martin, dealing extensively with Canada’s view of NATO in the 1970’s. (19 July 1967) BIL 1
    - Letter from P. de Burlet, Secretary of Sub-group 2, to Mr. Spaak through the Belgian Delegation on Canadian Secretary of State statement. (18 August 1967) FRE 1
    - FCM/67/109. Letter from F. C. Menne, Deputy Executive Secretary on the handing out of Canadian Secretary of State statement. (4 August 1967) ENG 1
  - Denmark’s contribution to the Future Tasks of the Alliance, Section 7
    - No.105.A.2.1. Danish Delegation. Letter to ASG Political Affairs, containing a statement made by the Danish Prime Minister on present perspectives on NATO policies and European market integration. (19 July 1967) ENG 1
- Report by Sub-group 1 East – West Relations (April 1967 – November 1967), 1967-04 - 1967-11; Volume 4; 35 Items
  - Meeting of Sub-Group 1 “East-West relations” on 18 April 1967, Section 1
    - United Kingdom Delegation. Preliminary contribution by British rapporteur Mr. Watson to the meeting of Sub-group 1 on 17 April. (14 April 1967) ENG 1
    - 20-02-5/1420/67 VSV. German Delegation. Political aims of the Alliance with regards to European security, the German problem and the nature of a European community. (14 April 1967) ENG 1
    - IS/67/60. Summary record by the Secretary of sub-group one of the first meeting of the Sub-group. (18 April 1967) FRE 1
    - GAS/67/45. Political Affairs Division, General Affairs Section. Summary of the first meeting of Sub-group 1 on the 18 April. (20 April 1967) ENG 1
  - The Secretary General distributes a paper on Soviet foreign policy, Section 2
    - United Kingdom Delegation. Letter from Mr. Watson to the Secretary General asking for his input into the Sub-group on East-West relations. (18 April 1967) ENG 1
    - GAS(67)41. Political Affairs Division, General Affairs Section. Draft letter and questionnaire to rapporteur of Sub-group one (East-West relations). (18 April 1967) ENG 1
    - PO/67/275. Private Office. Letter from Secretary General to British Ambassador on his input into the work of Sub-group 1, including the questionnaire on Soviet foreign policy and Europe. (19 April 1967) ENG 1
    - United Kingdom Delegation. Letter from British Ambassador to Secretary General discussing his questionnaire and how to effectively move forward with the Special Group’s objectives. (24 April 1967) ENG 1
    - PO/67/293. Private Office. Correspondence between Secretary General and British Representative on Soviet questionnaire. (27 April 1967) ENG 1
    - SG/67/168. Paper from the Secretary General Office on Soviet foreign policy and Europe for discussion in the Sub-group 1. (5 May 1967) ENG 1
  - Meeting of Sub-group 1 in May 1967, Section 3
    - Scenarios drawn up by the U.S. members of Sub-group 1 on the political aims of the Alliance. (9 May 1967) ENG 1
    - PO/67/316. Private Office. Secretary General’s comments on Mr. Schütz’ outline of the political aims of the Alliance. (11 May 1967) ENG 1
    - LLS/67/32. Summary of documentation from L. Lintall-Smith, for the second meeting of Sub-group 1, held 11 May 1967. (12 May 1967) ENG 1
    - GAS/67/56. Political Affairs Division, General Affairs Section. Summary of the second meeting of Sub-group 1, held 11 May 1967. (16 May 1967) ENG 1
  - Summary of the work done by Sub-Group 1, Section 4
    - AC/261/D/23. Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. Progress report by the rapporteurs of Sub-group 1. (18 May 1967) ENG 1
  - Discussions arising from the questionnaire on the Soviet Union, 6 May 1967. Meeting of Sub-group 1 in June 1967, Section 5
    - Belgian Delegation. Note for the rapporteurs of the sub-group 1 “L’Alliance atlantique, les relations Est-Ouest, les problèmes d’un réglement européen”. (20 June 1967) FRE 1
    - Danish comments on questions on the Soviet Union from the rapporteur’s paper of 6 May 1967. (24 June 1967) ENG 1
    - Netherlands Delegation. Comments on questions on the Soviet Union from the rapporteur’s paper of 6 May 1967. (19 June 1967) ENG 1
    - Note from J. Watson on the attitudes of Eastern European governments to improved economic relations with the West. (23 June 1967) ENG 1
    - GAS(67)66. Political Affairs Division, General Affairs Section. Note to the Secretary General enclosing German note on Professor Blishchenko article on European security. (27 June 1967) ENG 1
    - LLS/67/39. Summary of documentation from L. Lintall-Smith, for the third meeting of Sub-group 1. (30 June 1967) ENG 1
    - RS/67/85. Political Affairs section, Research Division. Summary of the third meeting of sub-group 1. (3 July 1967) ENG 1
    - RS/67/86. Political Affairs Division Research Section. Documentation list for Sub-group 1. (4 July 1967) ENG 1
  - Drafting the Paper on East-West relations, Détente and a European Settlement. Meeting of Sub-group 1 in September 1967, Section 6
    - SC/7-2458. Turkish Delegation. Mr. Nuri Birgi’s comments in relation with paper of sub-group 1 “Political aims of the Alliance”. (7 July 1967) ENG 1
    - United Kingdom Delegation. Measures towards a peaceful order in Europe. (12 July 1967) ENG 1
    - German and United Kingdom Delegation. Mr. Schütz and Mr. Watson draft report on East-West relations, Détente and a European settlement for the use of Sub-group 1. (11 September 1967) ENG 1
    - GAS/67/96. Political Affairs Division, General Affairs section. Summary of sub-group 1 meeting on 19 September. (19 September 1967) ENG 1
    - RS/67/109. Political Affairs Division Research Section. Report on meeting of Sub-group 1, 18 September. (20 September 1967) ENG 1
    - PO/67/709. Private Office. Secretary Generals comments to Mr. Watson on the work of Sub-group 1. (22 September 1967) ENG 1
    - RS/67/107. Political Affairs Division Research Section. Rerun of report on the discussion in Sub-group 1 on part 1 of the draft report. (25 September 1967) ENG 1
    - British Foreign Office. Letter to Secretary General M. Brosio on his contribution to the work of Sub-group 1. (27 September 1967) ENG 1
    - No. 5686. Netherlands Delegation. Letter from the Dutch Deputy Permanent Representative to the British Ambassador on Dutch Ambassador statement in last meeting of Sub-group 1. (21 September 1967) ENG 1
    - 20-02-5/3382/67 VSV. German Delegation. Letter from Deputy Permanent Representative, Mr. Oncken, to Secretary General discussing changes being made to the draft document. (28 September 1967) ENG 1
  - Summary and final report of Sub-group 1, Section 7
    - Summary of the work of sub-group 1 on the tasks of the Alliance: East-West relations and the German problem. (9 October 1967) ENG 1
    - Paper issued as part of AC/261-N/13(Rev) updated version of sub-group 1 Final report: East West Relations, Détente and a European Settlement. (November 1967) ENG 1
- Report by Sub-group 2 Inter-Allied Relations (April 1967 – October 1967), 1967-04 - 1967-10; Volume 5; 27 Items
  - Documents on the third meeting of Sub-group 2. NOTE: This section should be placed between section 5 and 6 in volume 5 as the document should be dated 5 May 1967 and not 5 April as mistakenly indicated, Section 1
    - IS/67/80. Secretary of sub-group 2. Note on the third meeting of sub-group 2. (5 April /actually May/ 1967) FRE 1
  - Documents on first meeting of Sub-group 2 on 17 April 1967, Section 2
    - S&A/67/39. Note from J. Leconte, Secretary of Sub-group 2, to the Secretary General briefing on the first meeting of Sub-group 2 on 17 April. (17 April 1967) FRE 1
    - Memorandum on the meeting of 17 April on Inter-Allied Relations. (April 1967) ENG 1
  - Response to questionnaire on “Inter-Allied Relations”, Section 3
    - S&A/67/40. Secretary of Sub-group 2. Questionnaire on “Inter-Allied Relations.” (21 April 1967) BIL. Annex: Belgian Delegation Questionnaire “Relations entre les Allies” (18 April 1967) FRE 1
    - Summary of a meeting in the office of the Secretary General held 24 April. (24 April 1967) ENG 1
    - Preliminary observations on the questionnaire of Sub-group 2. (26 April 1967) FRE 1
    - SG/67/166. Circulation to delegations of preliminary observations on the questionnaire of Sub-group 2. (2 May 1967) ENG 1
  - Second meeting of Sub-group 2 on 26 April 1967, Section 4
    - S&A/67/46. Secretary of Sub-group 2. Summary of the second meeting of sub-group 2. (27 April 1967) FRE 1
  - Preliminary documents running up to the third meeting of Sub-group 2 on 8 May 1967, Section 5
    - United States Delegation. Letters from Counsellor R. Bowie to Mr. Spaak regarding questions for the work of Sub-group 2. (5 May 1967) ENG 1
    - United Kingdom Delegation. Memo on the current state of the Alliance and its future. (5 May 1967) ENG 1
    - S&A/67/50. Secretary of sub-group 2. Summary of the third meeting of the Sub-group 2. (9 May 1967) FRE 1
  - Report on the activities of Sub-group 2, Section 6
    - Belgian Delegation. Activity report by rapporteur of Sub-group 2. (24 May 1967) FRE 1
  - The fifth round of discussions of Sub-group 2, Section 7
    - IS/67/119. Note from the secretary of Sub-group 2 informing US Representative Counsellor Bowie will not be attending the meetings of Sub-group 2 over the 2nd to the 4th July. (28 June 1967) FRE 1
    - Suggested outline for a report by the rapporteur of Sub-group 2. (3 July 1967) FRE 1
    - Suggested outline for a report by the rapporteur of Sub-group 2. (3 July 1967) ENG 1
    - IS/67/124. Note from the secretary of Sub-group 2, on the fifth meeting of the Group on 4 July. (5 July 1967) FRE 1
    - Note for the Secretary General, giving a formal summary of Mr. Spaak’s comments in the meeting of 4 July 1967. (6 July 1967) FRE 1
    - Danish Delegation. Letter by Ambassador Hjorth-Nielsen to Mr. Spaak with remarks on his report. (12 July 1967) ENG 1
  - Comments on sixth meeting of Sub-group 2 on 26 September 1967, Section 8
    - IS/67/149. Secretary for Sub-group 2. Notice to the representatives on a change of meeting date, from the 9-10 of October to the 2-3 October. (5 September 1967) FRE 1
    - IS/67/154. Secretary of Sub-group 2. Notice to the representatives on a change of meeting date, from 9-10th of October to 29th September. (8 September 1967) FRE 1
    - FCM/67/150. F.C. Menne, Deputy Executive Secretary. Discussion on the coming date for the next round of discussions by Sub-group 2. (11 September 1967) ENG 1
    - C-R(67)38. Council meeting on 13 September discussing possible dates of the next meeting of Sub-group 2. (29 September 1967) BIL 1
    - FCM/67/166. Letter from F.C. Menne to Minister Spaak on the possible absence of Icelandic Representative for the meeting on the 26th September. (22 September 1967) FRE 1
    - Draft report by Mr. Spaak, rapporteur of Sub-group 2, The Ideological Foundation and Unity of the Alliance. (19 September 1967) FRE 1
    - Draft report by Mr. Spaak, rapporteur of Sub-group 2, The Ideological Foundation and Unity of the Alliance. Draft of final paper. (19 September 1967) ENG 1
    - IS/67/160. Report by the Secretary of Sub-group 2 on the comments made after the draft report on the Ideological Foundation and Unity of the Alliance, just after the meeting on the 26th September. (29 September 1967) FRE 1
  - Final report by Sub-group 2 on inter-allied relations, Section 9
    - Report by Sub-group 2 rapporteur, Mr. Spaak, on Inter-Allied Relations (4 October 1967) FRE 1
- Report by Sub-group 3 The Future Security Policy of the Alliance (April 1967 – October 1967), 1967-04 - 1967-10; Volume 6; 23 Items
  - First meeting of Sub-group 3 on 18 April 1967, Section 1
    - AC/261-N/3. Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. Reminder for members of Sub-group 3 that its first meeting would be held 13th April 1967. (7 April 1967) BIL 1
    - United States Delegation. US Rapporteur’s preliminary outline as a basis for discussions on the first meeting of Sub-group 3. (17 April 1967) ENG 1
    - LT(67)36. Summary by Mr. L. Thiébault, acting Secretary of Sub-group 3, of a meeting of Sub-group 3 held on the 18th April. (18 April 1967) ENG 1
    - 1645/67/geheim. German Delegation. Proposals for amending the American draft. (5 May 1967) ENG 1
  - Second Meeting of Sub-Group 3 on 18 May 1967, Section 2
    - FCM/67/76. Note from F.C. Menne, Deputy Executive Secretary, on a change of dates for the next meeting of Sub-group 3. (5 May 1967) ENG 1
    - LT(67)59. Note from L. Thiébault, secretary of Sub-group 3, on a change of dates for the next meeting of Sub-group 3. (8 May 1967) BIL 1
    - FPD(67)20. Force Planning Directorate. Note on rôle of tactical military power in the future of the Alliance. (12 May 1967) ENG 1
    - United States Delegation. Revised outline to Sub-group 3 regarding future defence policy. (15 May 1967) ENG 1
    - United States Delegation. Draft status report on Sub-group 3. (16 May 1967) ENG 1
    - LT(67)68. Acting Secretary of sub-group 3. Brief summary of the meeting of Sub-group 3 on 18th May. (19 May 1967) ENG 1
    - DJV(67)2. Summary report from Mrs. D. Vincent, of the Economics and Finance Division, of the meeting of Sub-group 3 on 18th May. (19 May 1967) ENG 1
    - II A 3-86.60/1-636/67 VSV. German Delegation. Letter from the State Secretary of Foreign Affairs to the Secretary General detailing Germany’s input to the Sub-group’s work. (8 June 1967) ENG 1
    - APH/67/168. A.P. Hockaday’s note for rapporteur sub-group 3 Mr. Kohler on the report of Sub-group 3. (8 June 1967) ENG 1
    - Reply from F. Kohler to A.P. Hockaday on the work done by Sub-group 3 and his contribution. (23 June 1967) ENG 1
  - Status Report of Sub-Group 3, Section 3
    - United States Delegation. Memorandum by F. Kohler to the Secretary General containing a status report from Sub-group 3, along with an outline for the study of Future Defense Policy. (25 May 1967) ENG 1
  - Third and last meeting of Sub-Group 3 held in Washington, 21-22 September 1967, Section 4
    - United States Delegation. Letter from Secretary of Delegation S. Johnson, to Lord Coleridge, Executive Secretary, requesting news on whether a meeting in Washington would be possible for the other delegations. (24 May 1967) ENG 1
    - APH(67)150. Reply from Mr. Hockaday, acting ASG for Economics and Finance, to the American Delegation’s date proposal for next meeting. (30 May 1967) ENG 1
    - FCM/67/89. Response from Mr. Menne to the US Delegation on their letter of 24th May regarding dates of next meeting. (31 May 1967) ENG 1
    - Draft Report by F.D. Kohler, rapporteur sub-group 3, The Future Security Policy of the Alliance. (1 September 1967) FRE 1
    - Draft Report by F.D. Kohler, rapporteur sub-group 3, The Future Security Policy of the Alliance. (1 September 1967) ENG 1
    - Final Draft Report by F.D. Kohler, rapporteur Sub-group 3, The Future Security Policy of the Alliance. (25 September 1967) ENG 1
    - APH/67/280. Mr. Hockaday’s summary on the meeting held in Washington from 21-22 September. (26 September 1967) ENG 1
  - Final Draft Report by rapporteur Sub-group 3, Section 5
    - Final Draft Report by F.D. Kohler, rapporteur Sub-group 3, The Future Security Policy of the Alliance. (6 October 1967) ENG 1